Allen mss., 800-1972 LMC 2454
Lilly Library
- 16: Al-Bukhari, Muhammad Isma'il (810-870). Collection of traditions, copied in 1769., Muḥammad bin Muḥammad al-Mahdī al-Ḥulū; Mustamlī Bukhārī, Ismāʻīl ibn Muḥammad, -1043 (Bound 7)
  The third Sarlawḥ muzdawaj in both sides toward the outer edges contains two half-crowns (nīm-Tāj) and one crown (Tāj) that have scallop shape borders. They have foliated inside. All foliates are Maghribī Islīmī. The central design is a medallion, Shamsah, which is a repetitive geometrical design that has been made out of 8 complex Celtic knots. These have made a very small gilded medallion in the center. There are four katībahs at the top and bottom of each Sarlawḥ that are filled with an unknown poem from an unknown poet in praise of the book "Ṣaḥīḥ Bukhārī."
  Marginal notes are errata. Some of them have been cut while rebinding. However, the binder kept some, that were supposed to be cut, folded inside.
  Leather binding with an envelope flap with a gilded central mandorla (turanj) which is filled with an islīmī foliate frame and has been surrounded by four blue background lachak in corners. Two sar-turanj (head mandorla), with islīmī leaves and flowers foliates inside, are on both sides of the central turanj. It does not have sūkht leather art, but it has a gold stamp. There is a Khatāʾī shape foliates around the fromt and back covers. It has a double-square gilded stamp on front and back covers.
- 17: Faruh. Fourteen watercolors of heads, many apparently signed by the subjects of the drawing., 1949 - (Bound 8)
  Made in Istanbul.
- 18: Samadlobeli (A book of thanksgiving)., 26 July 1746 - (Box 8)
  Georgian manuscript of 55 leaves.
  Four full-page miniature, four other smaller miniatures.
  Presentation inscription from Prince Teimurazi to Sir Gore Ouseley, April 7, 1815, at St. Petersburg
- 19: Torcom, A. Diary of a Red Cross Sister about her experiences with a field hospital on the Eastern front in Warsaw and during the great Russian retreat., 23 January-24 October 1915 - (Bound 9)
  177 pages in Russian.
- 20: Romanian Charters (Box 9-14)
  - 20-1: Radu Mikhnea, Voevod and Gospodar of Ugrowallachia, 1601-1616. Charter in old Slavonic written in Cyrillic alphabet confirming grants of land to the sisterhood of "Elntse?" by various donors., 29 April 1607 - (Box 9)
    On vellum.
    480 x 345 mm.
    7115 A.C.
  - 20-2: Radu Mikhnea. Chrysobull (Golden Bull) in old Slavonic confirming a series of donations by his predecessors and making others to the monastery of St. Catherine at Bucharest., 27 June 1613 - (Box 10)
    Cyrillic alphabet.
    Vellum, 480 x 350 mm.
    7121 A.C.
  - 20-3: Radu Leon, Voevod and Gospodar of Ugrowallachia, 1664-1669. Chrysobull in old Slavonic, mentioning a monastery of Sinaia, a church of the Transfiguration, and making a grant to the Bishop Ananias and the Archimandrite Sophronius representing the monastery of St. Catherine at Bucharest., 17 July 1668 - (Box 11)
    Vellum, 495 x 410 mm.
    7176 A.C.
  - 20-4: Sherban Kantakuzen, Voevod and Gospodar of Ugrowallachia, 1673-1688. Chrysobull making a grant of lands to the monastery of SS. Michael and Gabriel and the abbot Daniel., 1681 - (Box 12)
    In Rumanian in Cyrillic alphabet.
    Vellum, 555 x 395 mm.
    7189 A.C.
  - 20-5: Michael Rakovita, Voevod and Gospodar of Moldavia and Wallachia, at various times from 1703-1744. Charter on paper., 24 June 1722 - (Box 13)
    7230 A.C.
  - 20-6: Michael Gregory Sturdza, Gospodar of Moldavia, 1834-1839. Charter making a grant to a monastery., 5 March 1835 - (Box 14)
    On paper.
    In Rumanian in Cyrillic script.
- 21: Chinese Punishments. Colored drawings on rice paper., Undated - (Box 15-17)
  Dismounted from bound volume and filed in brown box.
  25 drawings.
- 22: Orbeliani, Prince Sulkhan Saba, 1658-1725. Leks-koni. First dictionary of the Georgian language., Undated - (Bound 10)
  Copy of the Redaction B - finished before Orbeliani's mission to Europe in 1713.
  323 leaves.
  Written in red and black by the scribe Ioanne Laradze for Mzedchzbuk Orbeliani, Judge of Atskhur (a cousin of the author) in 1724.
  37 illustrations of letters or words.
  Ownership inscriptions of Prince George Nikolaevich Begration-Mulkhransky.
- 23: Hamayil. Collection of prayers, passages from the Bible, invocations...written for Menas, son of Sahak and his family., 21 February 1755 - (Box 18)
  Several miniatures in color.
  Scroll on 3 pieces of paper in cylindrical leather traveling case.
  9 x 17 cm.
  Armenian ms.
- 24: "Universals" (General Orders) of Elected Cossack Hetmans of Little Russia (The Ukraine) (Bound 11-13)
  - 24-1: Ioann Samoilovich, Hetman, 1672-1678. Order confirming the election of Pan Fedor Movchan as Colonel of the Priluki Regiment., 3 April 1678 - (Bound 11)
    Beturin.
    Paper.
  - 24-2: Ioann Skoropadsky, Hetman, 1709-[1722?]. Order addressed to the Colonel and other officers of Nezhim...granting the Lady Odaria Dyakovsky the village of Altynovka...Given at Glukhov., 9 November 1709 - (Bound 12)
  - 24-3: Danil Apostol, Hetman, 1727-1734. Order address to the village of Altynovka...confirming Skoropadsky's "Universal.", 13 December 1727 - (Bound 13)
    Given at Glukhov.
    In Russianised Ukranian hand on paper
- 25: Afanasiev, Alexander Nikolaevich, 1826-1871, Russian collector of folklore. Russkiya Zavyetniya Skazki., Undated - (Bound 14)
  A ms. collection of 77 bawdy folk tales.
  This may be a copy of all or part of "Russkiya Zavyetniya Skazki" published anonymously after A.N. Afanasiev's death in Geneva in 1872 in a small number of copies with the fictitious imprint "Vallam" Kilgour, No. I.
  Corresponds in some respects to the "Russkiya Narodniya Legendy" (Russian folk legends) which Afanasiev published in Russia in 1860 and then was withdrawn from sale at the demand of the Metropolitan Filaret of Moscow.
  Cloth-backed boards.
  Title on spine "Secret Russian Stories"
- 26: Sbornik. Collection of mss. of five Russian Chronicles., 16th-17th century - (Bound 15)
  440 pages.
  Written by three scribes in 17th century cursive script.
  In red, i.e. brown, contemporary Russian binding of leather over wooden boards, two clasps and catches.
  In beige slip case.
- 27: Stanislaus Augustus (Poniatowski). Last kind of Poland. Grant of hereditary nobility to his personal doctor Ioannes Godofredus Stolle., 30 December 1790 - (Box 19)
  Signed at Warsaw.
  In contemporary calf box, enclosed with 3 seals in silver gilt cases.
- 28: Catherine I. Empress of Russia, 1725-1727. Contemporary copy of a patent confirming the grant of hereditary nobility made to Nikita Demedich (now called Demidov)., 12 September 1720 - (Folio 1)
  7 p. (four leaves.)
  Original grant, September 12, 1720. Copy made 26 March, 1726.
  Illuminated on vellum.
- 29: "Gramoty" (Charters) of Tsars and Emperors of Russia (Box 20-36)
  - 29-1: Mikhail Fedorovich, Tsar, 1613-1645. Charter granting lands to Prince Mikhail Fedorovich Baryatinsky for his services in the defence of Moscow against the Poles., 1 August 1614 - (Box 20)
    7122 A.C.
    In old Russian, chancery hand.
    Marginal decorations, Tsar's seal in red wax. 380 x 365 mm.
  - 29-2: Mikhail Fedorovich, Tsar. Charter., 3 April 1614 - (Box 21)
  - 29-3: Mikhail Fedorovich, Tsar. Charter., 9 June 1621 - (Box 22)
  - 29-4: Alexei Mikhailovich, Tsar, 1645-1676. Charter granting lands to G.I. Byelkin for services to the Tsar's father in wars against Poles, Lithuanians and Circassians., 3 August 1649 - (Box 23)
    In old Russian in chancery hand.
    Decorated initial.
    580 x 450 mm.
    With Russian transcript
  - 29-5: Alexei Mikhailovich, Tsar. Charter on printed form with name and details inserted, granting an estate to the "Stryapchy" Frol Sinyavin., 24 November 1671 - (Box 24)
  - 29-6: Fedor Alexeievich, Tsar, 1676-1682. Printed charter to Alexei Aristophanovich Famendin., 12 June 1677 - (Box 25)
    With English translation.
  - 29-7: Fedor Alexeievich, Tsar. Printed charter to Peter Bogdanovich Chulkov., 4 October 1680 - (Box 26)
  - 29-8: Fedor Alexeievich, Tsar. Charter granting lands to Mikhail Timofeevich Likhachev in consideration of services to the Tsar's grandfather, father, the Tsar himself and his heirs., 30 January 1679 - (Box 27)
    In old Russian on vellum.
    Illuminated borders, seed pearls, amethysts, and turquoises.
    At Moscow, 820 x 620 mm.
    Removed from large gold-colored frame.
  - 29-9: Ioann and Peter Alexeievich, Co-Tsars, 1687-1689. Charter granting lands to Mikhail Timofeevich Likhachev., 3 August 1687 - (Box 28)
    Document in old Russian on vellum.
    Seed pearls.
    Moscow.
    590 x 480 mm.
    Removed from smaller gold-colored frame.
  - 29-10: Peter the Great, Tsar. Charter on printed form granting lands to Semyon Ivanovich Lyubovnikov for his services in the wars against the Turkish Sultan and the Khan of the Crimea., 9 December 1682 - (Box 29)
  - 29-11: Peter the Great, Tsar. Charter on printed form granting lands to Yury Vassilievich Kholopov of the Turkish Sultan and the Kahn of the Crimea., 30 November 1686 - (Box 30)
  - 29-12: Peter the Great, Tsar. Charter on printed form granting lands to Larion Yakimovich Nedoveskov for his services and relating the events leading up to the "perpetual peace" concluded with the King of Poland in 1686., Undated - (Box 31)
    Oversize.
  - 29-13: Peter the Great, Tsar. Charter on printed form granting lands to Vassili Ivanovich Volodimerov for his services to him and his descendants in perpetuity., June 1688 - (Box 32)
  - 29-14: Peter the Great, Tsar. Charter on printed form granting lands to Fedor Mikhailovich Danilov and his descendants in perpetuity for services rendered., July 1700 - (Box 33)
  - 29-15: Peter the Great, Tsar. Charter granting lands to Colonel Yakov Kondratievich Lizoguv of Chernigov for his services under Ivan Stepanovich Mazepa, Hetman... against the Khan of the Crimea., 3 September 1689 - (Box 34)
    Written in semi-uncial script.
    580 x 395 mm.
  - 29-16: Peter the Great, Tsar. Charter granting land to Colonel Lizogub., 23 January 1695 - (Box 35)
    On vellum in semi-uncial script.
    Elaborate ornamentations.
    720 x 530 cm.
  - 29-17: Peter the Great, Tsar. Charter on vellum granting lands to Stepan Otrokhov of Chernigov., 27 March 1690 - (Box 36)
    In semi-uncial script.
    Ornamented.
    660 x 480 mm.
- 30: Correspondence. Letters to W.E.D. Allen, many with enclosures, 1928-1972. (Box 1)
  Includes envelope of calling cards.
  Two boxes.
- 31: Certificate of gratitude to Allen for his presentation to the Georgian State Museum of Art., 27 August 1967 -
  Bound in brown leather.
- 32: Whitechurch Library Catalog, Nos. 1-6904., Undated - (Box 2)
- 33: Whitechurch Library Catalog, Authors Catalog A-Z., Undated - (Box 2)
- 34: Short catalogue of W.E.D. Allen's Collection of Icons and Carved Wood., Undated - (Box 1)
- 35: Gardening Plans., 1948-1950 - (Box 1)
  Written in an "Exercise Book" and containing several loose leaves laid in.
  Plans for vegetables, flowers.
- 36: Three bound volumes with brown spines and many blank pages., 1856-1961 -
  Volume A: Files 1-15, 1922, 1926-1929; records date, item, and occasional comment in red.
  Volume B: Allen family chronolgoy, 1856-1934; additions to library, 1957-1961.
  Volume C: Notes on Caucasia.
- 37: Box of pictures., Undated - (Folio 2, Box EMO)
- 38: Maps, large and small, about 42 in number., Undated - (Folio 3)
  Also includes one large picture of a woman.
- 39: Historical Miscellanies, Vols. 9, 10, 11., Undated - (Bound 16-18)
  Volumes bound in black with miscellaneous typed, holograph and printed material relating to Armenia, Georgia, Transylvania and Turkish history, 1916-1921.
- 40: Shanidze, Professor A. The Language and Script of the Caucasian Albanian., 16 August 1960 - (Box 1)
  Pencilled copy of report given to the 25th International Congress of the Orientalists held in Moscow, 9th to 16th August, 1960.
  Enclosed in a letter to Allen, 4 May 1961.
- 41: P.D.K. Three wateroclors of military uniforms., 1971? - (Box 1)
  Life Cuirassier, Russia, 1788; The Life Guards, 1821; Life Jager, Denmark, 1858.
  Life regiment of Horse and Foot.
  Each, 30 x 21 cm., white background.
- 42: Giorgi Merchule, a Georgian writer of the 10th century. Notes dated at Tbilisi, 1954 from Pavle, Inorogua. (Box 1)
  859 plus pages.
- 43: Thomas Phinn. Printed, typed, and pictorial piece related to Phin, 1814-1866., Undated - (Box 1)
  His family, his wine cellar, his ornamental objects, photograph and news clipping.
- 44: "As You Were.", Undated - (Box 1)
  Carbon typescript concerning Helene Langlois.
  9 pages.
- 45: Nosadze, V. "A Symbolism of Colors.", Undated - (Box 1)
  In pencil, "A very short summary of its contents."
- 46: Kudryatsev, O.V. "History of the Balkan Danube districts at the time of the Roman Empire.", 1959 - (Box 1)
  A review, typescript, and carbon.
- 47: Tolstoy, Count Aleksey Konstantinovich. The Death of Ivan the Terrible, tragedy in five acts., Undated - (Box 1)
  Translated by Humphrey R. A. Higgens.
  Carbon copy.
- 48: Reinhart Dozy's French translation of Ibn-Dihya's ms. account in Arabic of Al-Ghazal's embassy to the Vikings, published..., Undated - (Box 1)
  With notes.
- 49: Media. Parts II and III, pages 203-370 and 371-553., Undated - (Box 1)
- 50: Peoples of the Northern Caucasus, Part 8. Extract from "Outline of the History of the USSR.", Undated - (Box 1)
  Translation by Evan Ralphs, typescript.
  About 70 pages.
- 51: Description of present Osetiya or (of the Inhabitants) of the Inner Caucasus., Undated - (Box 1)
  Typescript, pages 136-153.
- 53: Roman Smal-Stocki. Terminological problems of Eastern European history., Undated - (Box 1)
  Xerox copy, 22 pages.
- 54: Anglo-Russian Contacts., Undated - (Box 1)
  Ms. with notes.
- 55: "The gods of Pagan Georgia." Bulletin of the Oriental Department of the Imperial Russian Archaeological Society, Vol. XIV., 1901 - (Box 1)
  Typed copy.
  Pages 1-29.
- 56: Chronological Table of Political Events in Georgian History., Undated - (Box 1)
  25 pages.
  Typed.
- 57: Georgian paganism by D. G. von Wesendonk., Undated - (Box 1)
  187 pages.
- 58: A list of Armenian and Azerbaijan leaders in Transcaucasia and Armenian historiogrpahy., Undated - (Box 1)
  Holograph.
- 59: On the date of the migration of the Mosokh from Armenia into Scanebi by N. J. Marr., Undated - (Box 1)
- 60: "Transcaucasia has not yet been exhaustively studied..." - first line of typed document., Undated - (Box 1)
  41 pages.
- 61: Through Mirdita in Winter by Stavro Th. Frashiri., Undated - (Box 1)
  93 pages.
- 62: High Jinks at the Mygdonian Consulate., Undated - (Box 1)
  5 holograph pages.
- 63: Three Georgian maps of the first half of the eighteenth century by W.E.D. Allen., Undated - (Box 1)
  42 pages.
- 64: Miscellaneous pieces., Undated - (Box 1)
  Includes cutting from Tule Tree, Oaxha; notes to Violet; copy about Colville letter; Society for PaleoMediterranean Studies (in French); Biographical notes; A.A. Pallis, The Phanariots (mimeo copy); The Turkish Minister of Interior's speech, 30 January 1947 (mimeo copy); Holograph draft of speech or article on Russian, Scandinavian and Irish influences; notes on a printed program.
- 65: Katib Celebi. Correspondence, notes, maps, photostats relating to Katib Celebi., 1925-1935 - (Box 3)
  Formerly owned by Professor Franz Taeschner.
- 66: Evliya Celebi, Turkish geographer. Seven volumes of photostats of Evliya's work, correspondence, articles, notes., 1954-1971 - (Bound 19-25)
- 67: Russian Embassies to the Georgian Kings by W.E.D. Allen., 1969 - (Box 3, Box 4)
  Galleys, page proofs (2 sets, corrected), drafts, typescripts, correspondence, reviews.
- 68: Box. The Ukraine. Correspondence, page proofs, articles, reviews, letter., 1947-1949 - (Box EMO)
- 69: Folio. The Four Rivers Area in the Russian Civil War, 1918-1919., Undated - (Folio 4)
  Four parts, original and carbon typescript and in pencil.
  With many maps.
- 70: Box. The Kurds. Holograph, typed and printed accounts., Undated - (Box EMO)
- 71: Box. The Caucasus. Corrected typescript., Undated - (Box EMO)
- 72: Box. The Caucasus. Correspondence and printed material., 1939-1951 - (Box EMO)
- 73: Box. The Caucasus. Typed and holograph articles., Undated - (Box EMO)
- 74: Box. Anatolia. Correspondence and source material., Undated - (Box EMO)
- 75: Box. Anatolia. Pictures and printed material., Undated - (Box EMO)
- 76: Box. Anatolia. Typed material., Undated - (Box EMO)
- 77: Box. Anatolia. Typed material., Undated - (Box EMO)
- 78: Box. Anatolia. Typed material., Undated - (Box EMO)
- 79: Box. Anatolia. Typed material., Undated - (Box EMO)
- 80: Box. Anatolia. Typed material., Undated - (Box EMO)
- 81: Box. Anatolia. Typed material., Undated - (Box EMO)
- 82: Box. Anatolia. Tours I., 1944-1949 - (Box EMO)
- 83: Box. Anatolia. Tours II., 1944-1949 - (Box EMO)
- 84: Box. Turkistan Tarihi. (German version.) Pages 1-359., Undated - (Box EMO)
- 85: Box. Turkistan Tarihi. (German version.) Pages 360-784., Undated - (Box EMO)
- 86: Box. Turkistan Tarihi. Typed and printed material., Undated - (Box EMO)
- 87: Box. Abyssinia. Guerilla war. Correspondence., 1941-1942 - (Box EMO)
  Includes Diary of W.E.D. Allen, 1941.
- 88: Box. Abyssinia. Guerilla War. Correspondence and notes., 1941-1942 - (Box EMO)
  Includes maps
- 89: Peoples, Language and History of the Hittite Race. A compendium., Undated - (Box 5)
- 90: The Chronicles of the Meskhian Psalter., Undated - (Box 5)
  Translation by A. Gujushvile.
- 91: A Georgian Relief in Repousse Silver., 1938 - (Box 5)
  With photograph and correspondence.
- 92: Lists of the Feudal Lords and of the Bishoprichs of Meskhet'i., Undated - (Box 5)
- 93: The Origin of American man and Japhetic linguistics by N.Y. Marr., 1926 - (Box 5)
  Translated by G.C. Wheeler.
- 94: George Mertchul's Life of St. Gregory of Khandzt'a by N.Y. Marr., Undated - (Box 5)
- 95: The Territory of the Turkish Lazistan by N.Y. Marr., Undated - (Box 5)
- 96: Three Months in Turkish Georgia., Undated - (Box 5)
  82 pages.
- 97: Vakhushti's Description of Samtzhke. Being a Study in the historical geography and topography of south-western Georgia (the upper valley of the Kura and the Chorokh valley)., Undated - (Box 5)
  With introduction and notes by W.E.D. Allen.
  Typed copy with corrections and notes.
  33 pages and 56 pages.
- 98: Materials relating to George Jacob. Five small paper-covered carbon copies., 1932-1934 - (Box 5)
  Formerly owned by Franz Taeschner.
  Includes Bibliographie meiner Veroffentlichungen, 3 pages; Bibliothekarisches, 4 pages; Reimstudien, ein erster Versuch zu einer Geschichte des Reims von George Jacob, 43 pages; Zur Geschichte des bindenden Endreims, 4 pages; Deutsche Kosenamen als Familiennamen, zusammengestellt von G. Jacob, 5 pages.
- 99: Boxes I and II. Printed materials., Undated - (Box EMO)
  Some works by W.E.D. Allen; other pieces inscribed to Allen; numerous reprints.